A Guide to the Augustus Jackson Brundage Papers 1981.0001
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Augustus Jackson Brundage Papers
undated, 1884-1981
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1981.0001
6 Linear Feet
Born in Danbury, Connecticut, Augustus Jackson Brundage attended the Danbury public schools before entering the Connecticut Agricultural College at Storrs in September 1906. He was appointed State Club Leader for the Extension Service of the Connecticut Agricultural College and the United States Department of Agriculture in 1917. Mr. Brundage retired from the University in 1948 but remained active with the 4-H.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to Historical Manuscripts and Archives Division (now Archives & Special Collections) of the University of Connecticut Libraries in three sections. In 1975, Ruth Brundage donated the photographs and memorabilia pertaining to the class of 1910. In 1981, she donated the 4-H glass slides. The remainder of the collection was donated in July of 1987 by Mrs. Peg [Brundage] Christie after her mother's death.
Arrangement
Series I: Personal (1884-1981); Series II: Employment (1913-1971); Series III: Family (1909-1972); Series IV: Photographs (undated, 1910-1963); Series V: Scrapbooks and ephemera (undated, 1962).
Biography
Born in Danbury, Connecticut, on 19 August 1890, Augustus Jackson Brundage attended the Danbury public schools before entering the Connecticut Agricultural College at Storrs in September 1906. Brundage graduated in 1910 and in 1912 accepted the position of caretaker at the H. B. Mallory estate in Danbury. He also served as supervisor of the teaching of agriculture in the Mansfield and Lebanon schools before his appointment as State Club Leader for the Extension Service of the Connecticut Agricultural College and the United States Department of Agriculture in 1917.
Brundage served as the Director of the International 4-H Leader Training School at Eastern State Exposition in Springfield from 1923 through 1930. He served on numerous national committees for the promotion of 4-H Club work. Mr. Brundage retired from the University in 1948 but remained active with the 4-H.
Married in 1915 to Ruth Miller, also a C.A.C. graduate, the Brundage's had four children. Two of the boys, Granville and Roger, were killed in action during World War II. The Brundage pool (Greer Field House) on the University campus is named in their honor.
Brundage was a member of the House of Pioneers of Epsilon Sigma Phi, a national fraternity of Extension workers, and of Alpha Gamma Rho, a national college social fraternity.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of correspondence, memorabilia, clippings, publications films and photographs relating to Brundage's interests and career. Topics include education, agriculture, University and Connecticut history, the 4-H and family materials.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
On Being American Dodd Call No. C5342
RUS Dodd Call No. B5460
The Lookout (available in the University Archives), November 1901, December 1901, August 1902, March 1903, September 1905, January 1906, September 1906, June 1907, June 1908, February 1912.
Bibliography
Walter Stemmons>, Connecticut Agricultural College—A History, Storrs: Connecticut Agricultural College, 1931.
Slides (photographs); Scrapbooks; Educators; Photographs; Publications (documents); Memorabilia; Manuscripts (document genre); Correspondence; Moving images
- Series I: Personal, 1884-1981
  - Correspondence, 1930, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Education memorabilia, 1910-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Connecticut history, 1884-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- Series II: Employment, 1913-1971
  - Alumni publications, 1933-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Class of 1910 reunions, 1935, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Emeritus, 1956-1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - History, 1928-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - James Barnett pamphlets, 1969, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Testimonials (for others), 1942-1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Testimonials (memorabilia), 1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Testimonials (original letters), 1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - University Correspondence, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Varsity letters, [1910] (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 4-H Extension Newsletters, 1931-1944 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 4-H Round Up programs, 1924-1931 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 4-H Memorabilia, 1914-[1934] (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 4-H Pamphlets about China, 1953-1968 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Extension publications, 1953-1979 (Box 2, Folder 21-23)
  - Farm and Home Week guide, 1935-1944 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Series III: Family, 1909-1972
  - Brundage, Granville, 1943-1961 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - Brundage, Roger, 1939-1964 (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
  - Storrs Cemetery Association, 1954-1972 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
- Series IV: Photographs, undated, 1910-1963
  - Class of 1910, undated (Box 3)
  - Class of 1910 (oversize) (Box 4)
  - 16mm film, undated (Box 5)
    - Machine plowing and planting at Lee Farm, 1942; 1981-0001/MP 1; Film reformatted, 2013.; 1 film reel: si., col. (Kodachrome); 16mm. (Cassette 1981-0001/VR 1 I, Disk 1981-0001/DVD 1 R, Reel 1981-0001/MP 1 P)
      Access
      Original not available due to fragility. Use reference copy.
      Scope and Content Note
      Written on box: "Lee Farm" "[farming]"; "Albert E. Wilkinson Extension Service4 Storrs, Conn." Written on cardboard in box: "Lee Farm - [misc] - maching [plowing]" Film depicts young men transplanting seedlings and several examples of machine farming at Lee Farm in Coventry, CT. A tractor-mounted tiller, probably on a McCormick-Deering Farmall tractor, is shown at 1 min. 30 sec. A horse-drawn plow is used at 2 min. 13 sec. A tractor with what is mostly likely a John Deere 290 corn planter attached is shown at 2 min. 30 sec. Albert E. Wilkinson served as the Extension Service's vegetable gardening specialist as part of his duties in the Horticulture Department at the Connecticut Agricultural College at Storrs starting in 1930. Wilkinson shot over 1000 feet of film documenting vegetable growing and harvesting throughout the country to share with his classes and during community movie nights throught the Extension Service Program. More information on the Extension Service program can be found in the Cooperative Extension Service collection (MSS19700003). Total run time 3 min. 47 sec.
    - Fruit blossoms, CWLA, Lee Farm, 1942; 1981-0001/MP 2; Film reformatted, 2013.; 1 film reel: si., col. (Kodachrome); 16mm. (Cassette 1981-0001/VR 1I, Disk 1981-0001/DVD 1 R, Reel 1981-0001/MP 2 P)
      Written on box: "Fruit blossoms & Lee Farm"; "Albert E. Wilkinson Extension Service Storrs, Conn." Film begins at 3 min. 49 sec. and documents ornamental flowers and flowering fruit trees at Lee Farm in Coventry, CT. Film also depicts young women doing farm work as part of the Connecticut Women's Land Army (CWLA). The women use hoes, hand plows, and a tractor-mounted tilling machine. This video was most likely taken the same day as the machine plowing video (1081.0001/MP1) as several of the young men from the first video can be seen in the background. More information on the CWLA can be found in the University of Connecticut Agriculture and Resource Economic Department Records collection (MSS1998-0069). Photographs of the CWLA can be found in the University of Connecticut Photograph Collection (MSS1998-0010). Albert E. Wilkinson served as the Extension Service's vegetable gardening specialist as part of his duties in the Horticulture Department at the Connecticut Agricultural College at Storrs starting in 1930. Wilkinson shot over 1000 feet of film documenting vegetable growing and harvesting throughout the country to share with his classes and during community movie nights throught the Extension Service Program. 3 min. 46 sec. run time.
    - Potato harvesting at Lee Farm, circa 1940; 1981-0001/MP 3; Film reformatted, 2013.; 1 film reel: si., col. (Kodachrome); 16mm. (Disk 1981-0001/DVD 1 R, Cassette 1981-0001/VR 1 I, Reel 1981-0001/MP 3 P)
      Written on box: "Albert E. Wilkinson Storrs, Connecticut (University of Conn.)" This short film (run time 3 min.) contains footage of men harvesting potatoes, probably on Lee Farm. At 8 min. 30 sec. the harvester (digger) can be seen, which required twelve men to drive the tractor, sort, bag, and load potatoes on to a second truck. Researchers of the history of agricultural technology may be interested in this video. Albert E. Wilkinson served as the Extension Service's vegetable gardening specialist as part of his duties in the Horticulture Department at the Connecticut Agricultural College at Storrs starting in 1930. Wilkinson shot over 1000 feet of film documenting vegetable growing and harvesting throughout the country to share with his classes and during community movie nights throught the Extension Service Program. Total run time 3 min. 47 sec.
    - Potato field tour at the farm of Louis L. Grant, 1946; 1981-0001/MP 4; Film reformatted, 2013.; 1 film reel: si., col. (Kodachrome): 16mm. (Disk 1981-0001/DVD 1 R, Cassette 1981-0001/VR 1 I, Reel 1981-0001/MP 4 P)
      Written on box: "Potato field day L.L. Grant." Footage is of a demonstration of potato digging machine at the farm of Louis L. Grant in Attwaugan, Connecticut on September 9, 1946. The end of the video depicts close shots of the machinery and would be of interest to historians of agricultural technology. Film most likely shot by Albert E. Wilkinson. For Wilkinson's report on the field tour see box 4 of the Cooperative Extension Service collection (MSS19700003) Total run time 3 min. 49 sec.
    - Potato harvesting, circa 1943; 1981-0001/MP 5; Film reformatted, 2013.; 1 film reel: si., col. (Kodachrome); 16mm. (Disk 1981-0001/DVD 1 R, Cassette 1981-0001/VR 1 I, Reel 1981-0001/MP 5 P)
      Written on box: "potatoe harvesting" " [?] Potato [?]" "Dust & [?] [1946]"; "Albert E. Wilkinson University of Conn. Storrs, Conn." Footage depicts potato harvesting demonstration at the farm of noted jurist Simon S. Cohen in Rockville, Connecticut. Video begins at 14 min. 44 sec. Potatoes are unearthed by a digging machine, collected in baskets, and then put in barrells which are picked up by men using small crane mounted to flatbed truck. A number of black farm employees are shown packing the potatoes into barrells and two children are prominant at the start of the film (15 min. 25 sec).The machinery depicted here is less developed than that shown in 1981-0001/MP3 and 1981-001/MP4. At 15 min. 55 sec. the film cuts, possibly to Lee Farm, also to potato harvesting. In this portion the equipment shown in 1981-001/MP3 is shown and several women are assisting with sorting the potatoes. Albert E. Wilkinson served as the Extension Service's vegetable gardening specialist as part of his duties in the Horticulture Department at the Connecticut Agricultural College at Storrs starting in 1930. Wilkinson shot over 1000 feet of film documenting vegetable growing and harvesting throughout the country to share with his classes and during community movie nights throught the Extension Service Program. Total run time 3 min. 49 sec.
    - Potato harvesting, winter weather, 1944; 1981-0001/MP 6; Film reformatted, 2013; 1 film reel: si., col. (Kodachrome); 16mm. (Disk 1981-0001/DVD 1 R, Cassette 1981-0001/VR 1 I, Reel 1981-0001/MP 6 P)
      Written on box: "potato [digging]" "ice storms John Morris [soil sh...?] "[slanety ? potato ? harvesting?]" "Albert E. Wilkinson Hillside Rd. Storrs Conn." Video footage depicts the aftermath of an ice storm and minor snow accumulation at the farm of John E. Morris in Wethersfield, CT. Bags of potatoes are shown in the fields waiting to be gathered. The storm likely occoured in early November, 1944. Total run time 1 min. 24 sec.
  - 4-H photographs (oversize), undated (Box 5)
  - Color photographs of World War II memorial (Granville Brundage, oversize), undated (Box 6)
- Series V: Scrapbooks and ephemera, undated, 1962
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 5)
  - Class banner, undated [1910] (Box 5)
  - Class of 1910 banner and smock, undated (Box 5)
  - Clippings and photographs, undated (Box 5)
  - Maps of Mansfield, undated (Box 5)
  - Cetificate of Merit (Chinese), 1962 (Box 5)